Okay, so now that we successfully have all of our typing logic sorted out, I'm just typing
random characters here, and our scrolling logic sorted out, you'll see that our timer is
still at 60 seconds.
So we need to implement our timer related logic, and we also want to calculate our words per
minute.
Okay, so let's go ahead and jump into the code.
Okay, so I'm actually going to go ahead and maybe minimize this just for now, and we're
going to go back up to the top here, and we're actually going to need a few more variables,
and we're going to require a time left, which is going to be a number.
So normally this would be 60 seconds, but I'm just going to make it six seconds for
our testing, and we're going to have a timer interval.
So we're going to use set interval, and we are going to run this interval every one
second.
So it's going to tick down one second at a time, it's going to run this function, it's
going to keep checking, is there any time left, we're essentially going to bring this number
down 60, 59, 58, and then once it gets to zero, then we are going to actually end our
test.
So we're going to call another function.
Okay, and we also want to know whether or not we've started typing.
So as you'll notice, the timer doesn't actually start in our final version until we start
typing.
So we're going to have a let for this typing started, is going to be equal to false.
Okay, and I think that's it for our variables that we're going to need.
Of course, you could make this count down whatever you want, I'm just going to keep it
simple and make it 60 seconds to calculate our words per minute nicely.
Okay, so from here, we are going to go ahead and below this function, we'll comment out
a title for starting our count down timer, and it'll make a function called start timer,
and we are going to say if we have not typing started yet, then we're going to set this
typing started boolean to be equal to true.
And then inside of this, we're going to set our interval.
So timer interval is going to be equal to set interval bracket brackets again, so this is
going to be an arrow function curly brackets semi colon.
So basically this is going to trigger our set interval, and this is going to run every
second.
So after our curly bracket at the end here, we'll put a comma and then put 1000 milliseconds,
which is equal to one second, so that means anything inside of this timer interval set
interval is going to execute every one second.
So our time left, we're going to decrement by one, so we're just going to use minus minus
to decrement our time left, and then we want to also update our timer element.
And we're going to update the text context, and this is going to be equal to, I'm going
to use back ticks for a template string, time left, and dollar sign curly brackets, and
we're going to pass in our time left, and then we'll put s at the end for seconds.
And then if time left is less than or equal to zero, you'll usually just be zero, but
we'll put that just in case. We're going to clear our interval of timer interval.
So this is why it is important to name your set intervals so that they can be cleared
effectively.
So this is going to end this execution here, and then we're going to want to end our test.
And so we'll just create a stand in function for this for now, and the test, and we want
to display the final score.
For now, we're just going to say function and test, and we'll just do an alert, test
is over.
Okay, so let's go ahead and test what we have here so far.
Okay, so I'm going to type something, and you'll see that, okay, that didn't work.
And you know why that didn't work?
It's because we did not call our start timer function.
So that is a very important thing that we need to do.
And this is something we're actually going to do in our event listener.
So we are going to, as I mentioned before, start our timer when we hear our first key
down event.
That's when we're going to start our timer.
Okay, we can go ahead and minimize that again, and let's try that again.
Okay, so now, if I type, you can see 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, and the test is over.
Okay, so we're out of time.
Okay, so we can see that our interval is working, and you can see that we have hit our
end test function.
Now we actually need it to do the right thing when we're ending our test.
So let's go back and instead of an alert here, we are going to want to switch our timer
element, text, content, you'll see that it was stuck at time left 1S, and they just
kind of stayed there.
And so instead, we'll use back ticks again, times up.
Okay, so we're going to change that.
And our final score element dot text content is going to be equal to final WPM.
And then we'll leave that blank for now, we're going to need to calculate that.
But for now, we'll leave that blank.
Text container style dot display equals none.
And our try again button style display is going to be equal to block.
So we want to show our try again button.
Okay, so let's try that again.
Okay, and we're counting down here.
Okay, so that's definitely looking better.
We have our final words for a minute, but we haven't calculated it yet.
And then we have our time's up.
And then we have our try again button, which of course does not do anything yet.
But this is right for how we want our UI to change.
Okay, so the last thing we need to do is actually calculate our words per minute.
And we're going to pass in that number there.
Okay, so let's go back and right below our end test function, comment out calculate words
per minute with error adjustment.
So we are going to adjust for errors.
Basically the way I decided to do it was for every one error, you lose a word per minute.
Okay, so function calculate WPM.
Okay, and we're going to create a constant called words typed.
And this is going to be equal to our total type.
So remember we have a long string of every character that we've typed.
And we're going to use trim to remove any spaces.
And then we're going to split and we're going to use slash backslash s plus.
And then slash again.
And this is a reg x statement.
And it's going to allow us to split on every space.
And then we want to actually get the length of that.
So it's going to have an array of words and we want that length.
So that is going to show us every word that we've typed will actually console log to show
how that's going to look.
So console log our words typed.
And then we'll also console log this here as well.
Show what I mean.
Okay, let's check that out.
Okay, so I'm going to actually try this time.
Okay, so that didn't actually work.
Again, I didn't call this.
So that's important.
Always call your functions when you make them.
So I'm going to call this at the end of our end test year.
Very important to call your functions.
Okay, let's try that one more time.
Okay, we also want to type in the console.
Okay, okay, and you can see that it is five.
And you'll see that we have five words that I typed in an array.
And it's split every time that I added a space.
So that is accurate.
I typed five words, not permitted, but in six seconds.
Okay, so let's go ahead and continue with our calculate words for a minute here.
And from here, we want to get our base WPM and this is going to be equal to math round.
So we want a whole number and we're going to use words typed, divided by 60.
And then times 60 to get back to a minute.
So in our case, the final test will be 60 seconds.
But if you wanted to change it to be 30 or in our case, six seconds, you would actually
change this number here.
So let's say that I had words typed, divided by six.
This should give me an accurate base words for a minute in my six second test.
Okay, and from here, we're going to have our adjusted WPM and this is going to be equal
to math max and it's going to take our base WPM minus errors comma zero.
And the reason we have this is let's say that our base words for a minute was five, but
we had 10 errors.
We want the minimum adjusted words for a minute to be zero.
That's why math max is going to take the bigger of these two numbers.
And then we're going to return our adjusted words per minute, okay.
And then we're actually going to call this inside of our template string here.
So do dollar sign, really bracket and calculate WPM and bracket.
Okay, and we can remove this from the bottom.
Okay, so let's give that a try.
All right, so I'll start typing, oh, vivid, oops, vivid, pair, nest, okay.
So you can see that I actually got 50.
So I divided by six and then I times that by 60 to get to what it would be over the course
of a minute.
So I actually typed the equivalent of 50 words a minute in six seconds, which is pretty
good.
Okay, so we have successfully started our timer when we trigger that first event listener
when we type any character and our timer is successfully counting down.
And when we've reached the end of that countdown, we're successfully showing our end
of test UI and we're successfully calculating our words per minute.
Okay, so in the next one, we want to add the functionality to our try again to be
able to reset our test.
And we also want to make sure that if users are on a mobile device, they are going to
get a message to let them know that they need to run it on their computer.
All right, so let's tackle that in the next one.
I'll see you then.
Bye for now.